In this lesson, we'll
do a deep dive into
another advanced RAG technique, auto-merging.
An issue with the naive approach
is that you're retrieving a
bunch of fragmented context chunks to
put into the LLM context menu,
and the fragmentation
is worse the smaller your
chunk size. Here, we use an
auto-merging heuristic to merge
smaller chunks into
a bigger parent chunk to help
ensure more coherent context. Let's check
out how to
set it up. In this section, we'll talk
about auto-merging retrieval. An
issue with the standard
RAG pipeline
is that you're retrieving a
bunch of fragmented context chunks
put into the LLM context window,
and the fragmentation is worse the
smaller your
chunk size. For instance, you
might get back two or
more retrieved context chunks in
roughly the same section, but there's
actually no guarantees on the ordering
of these
chunks. This can potentially hamper
the alum's ability to synthesize
over this retrieved context within its
context window. So what
auto-merging retrieval does is
the following. First, define
a hierarchy of
smaller chunks linking to bigger parent
chunks, where each parent
chunk can have some number of
children. Second,
during retrieval, if the set
of smaller chunks linking to
a parent chunk
exceeds some percentage threshold, then we
merge smaller chunks into the bigger
parent chunk. So
we retrieve the bigger parent
chunk instead to help ensure
more coherent context. Now let's check
out how to set this up.
This notebook will introduce
the various components needed to construct an auto-merging
retriever with Llama
index. The various
components will be
covered in detail.
And similar to the previous
section, at the end,
Adupam will show you
how to experiment with parameters and
evaluation with TruEra. Similar to before,
we'll load in
the OpenAI API
key, and we'll load
this using a convenience
helper function in our utils file. As
with the previous lessons, we'll also
use the how to
build a career in
AI PDF. And as before, we
also encourage you to try out
your own PDF files as well.
We load in
41 document objects, and
we'll merge them into a single large document,
which makes this more amenable for text
blending with our advanced retrieval methods.
Now we're ready to
set up our auto-merging retriever. This
will consist of
a few different components,
and the first step is to define what we
call a
hierarchical node parser. In
order to use an
auto-version retriever, we need
to parse our nodes
in a hierarchical fashion. This means
that nodes are parsed in decreasing
sizes and
contain relationships to their parent
node. Here we demonstrate how
the node parser works with a
small example. We
create a toy
parser with small chunk
sizes to demonstrate. Note
that the chunk sizes
we use are 20, 48, 5, 12,
and 128. You can change the
chunk sizes to any sort of
decreasing order that you'd like. Here we do
it by a factor of four.
Now let's get the
set of nodes from the document.
What this
does is this actually returns all nodes. This returns
all leaf nodes, intermediate nodes, as
well as parent nodes. So
there's going to be
a decent amount of overlap
of information and content between
the leaf,
intermediate, and parent nodes. If we only
want to retrieve the leaf nodes, we can
call a function within
Llama index called "gat
leaf nodes," and we
can take a look
at what that looks like.
In this example, we
call gat leaf nodes on
the original set of nodes. And we take
a look at the 31st node
to look at
the text. We see that
the text trunk is actually fairly
small. And this is an example of
a leaf node, because a leaf node
is the smallest chunk size
of 128 tokens. Here's how
you might go about strengthening your math background to
figure out what's important
to know, etc. Now
that we've shown what a
leaf node looks like,
we can also explore
the relationships. We can print the
parent of the above node
and observe that
it's a larger chunk containing the text of
the leaf node, but also more.
More concretely, the parent
node contains 512 tokens,
while having four leaf nodes
that contain 128 tokens. There's
four leaf nodes because the chunk
sizes are divided by a
factor of four each time. This
is an example of
what the parent node of
the 31st leaf node looks
like. Now that we've
shown you what the
node hierarchy looks like, we
can now construct our index.
We'll use the OpenAI LLM
and specifically GPT 3.5 Turbo. We'll
also define a service context object containing
the LLM embedding model and
the hierarchical node parser. As with the
previous notebooks, we'll use
the "bge small en embedding model." The
next step is to
construct our index.
The way the
index works is
that we actually construct a
vector index on specifically the leaf
nodes. All other
intermediate and parent nodes are
stored in a doc
store and are retrieved dynamically during retrieval.
But what we actually fetch during
the initial top
K embedding lookup
is specifically the
leaf nodes, and
that's what we embed. You see
in this code that we define
a storage context
object, which by default is initialized
with an in-memory document store. And
we call "storage_context.docstore.addDocuments "to add
all nodes to this in-memory doc
store. However, when we create our vector store
index, called auto-merging index,
right here, we only
pass in the leaf
nodes for vector indexing. This means
that, specifically, the
leaf
nodes are embedded using the embedding model
and also indexed. But
we also pass in the storage context
as well as the
service context. And so the vector index
does have knowledge of the
underlying doc store that
contains all the nodes.
And finally, we persist
this index. If you've
already built this index
and you want to
load it from storage, you can
just copy and paste this block
of code, which
will rebuild the
index if it doesn't exist or
load it from storage. The last
step now that we've defined the
auto-merging index is to set up the retriever
and run the query engine. The
auto-merging retriever is what controls
the merging logic. If
a majority of children
nodes are retrieved for a given parent,
they are swapped out for the
parent instead. In order
for this merging to
work well, we set
a large top-k for the leaf nodes.
And remember, the leaf
nodes also have a
smaller chunk size of
128. In order to
reduce token usage, we
apply a re-ranker after
the merging has taken
place. For example, we might retrieve the top
12, merge and have a
top 10, and then re-rank into a
top 6. The top end
for the re-ranker may seem larger,
but remember that the base chunk
size is only 128 tokens, and then
the next parent above
that is
512 tokens. We import a class
called auto-merging retriever, and then we
define a sentence transformer re-rank module. We combine
both the auto-merging retriever and the
re-rank module into our
retriever query engine, which handles
both retrieval and synthesis. Now that
we've set this whole thing
up end-to-end, let's actually test
what is the importance of networking
in AI
as an example question,
we get back a
response. We
see that it says networking
is important in AI because
it allows individuals
to build a strong
professional network and
more. The next
step is to
put it all together. And we'll create two
high-level functions, build auto-merging index,
as well as
get auto-merging query engine. And this
basically captures all
the steps that we just showed you in
the first function, build auto-merging index.
We'll use the hierarchical node parser
to parse out
the hierarchy of child
to parent nodes we'll define the service context
and we'll create a vector store index
from the leaf nodes
but also linking to the document store
of all the
nodes the second function,
get auto-merging query engine,
leverages our auto merging
retriever which is able to dynamically
merge leaf nodes
into parent nodes and
also use our re-rank
module and then combine
it with the overall retriever
query engine. So we build the index
using the build auto-merging
index function using the
original source document, the
LLM set to GPT
3.5 turbo, as well
as the merging index as a
save directory. And
then for the
query engine, we call get auto
merging query engine
based on the index, as well
as we set a similarity top K
of equal to six.
As a next step,
Anupam will show you
how to evaluate the auto-merging
retriever and also iterate
on parameters using TruEra.
We encourage you to try out your own
questions as well and also
iterate on the parameters of
auto-merging retrieval. For instance, what happens
when you change the trunk
sizes or the top K or
the top N for the re-ranker?
Play around with it and tell us
what the results are.
That was awesome, Jerry.
Now that you have set up the auto-merging
retriever, let's see how we can evaluate
it with the RAG
triad and compare its
performance to the basic
RAG with experiment tracking.
Let's set up
this auto-merging new index. You'll
notice that it's two
layers. The lowest layer chunk, the leaf
nodes, will have a
chunk size of
512, and the next layer up in
the hierarchy is a
chunk size of 2048, in the hierarchy is
a chunk size of 2048, meaning
that each parent will have
four leaf nodes of
512 tokens each. The
other pieces of setting this
up are exactly the
same as what Jerry
has shown you earlier.
One reason you may want to
experiment with the two-layer auto-merging
structure is that it's simpler.
Less work
is needed to create the
index, as well as in the
retrieval step, there is
less work needed because all the third-layer
checks go away. If
it performs comparably well, then
ideally we want to
work with a simpler structure.
Now that we have created
the index with this two-layer
auto-merging structure. Let's set up
the auto-merging engine for this setup. I'm
keeping the top
K at the same value
as before, which is 12. And
the re-ranking step will also
have the same and equal six.
This will let us do a
more direct head to head
comparison between this application setup
and the three-layer auto-merging hierarchy app
that Jerry had set up earlier.
Now let's set
up the Tru Recorder with this
auto-merging engine and we
will give this an app ID of
app 0. Let's now load some questions for
evaluation
from the generated questions.txt file that
we have set up earlier, now we can
define the running of these evaluation
questions for each
question in
eval, we are going to set things up
so that the Tru Recorder object,
when invoked with
the run evals, will record the
prompts, responses, and the evaluation results, leveraging the
query engine. Now that our
evaluations have completed, let's take a
look at the leaderboard. We
can see that app
0 metrics here. Context
relevance seems low.
The other two metrics
are better. This is with our two-level
hierarchy with 512 as the leaf node chunk
size and the parent
being 2048 tokens, so four leaf
nodes per parent node now
we can run the
true dashboard and take a look at the
evaluation results at the
record level at the
next layer of detail. Let's examine the app
leaderboard. You can see
here that after processing
24 records, the context
relevance at an aggregate
level is quite low, although
the app is doing better
on answer relevance and
groundedness. I can select the
app. Let's now look at
the individual records of app
0 and see how the evaluation
scores are for
the various
records. You can scroll to the
right here and look
at the scores for
answer relevance, context relevance,
and groundedness. Let's pick
one that has low context
relevance. So here's one. If
you click on it, you'll
see the more detailed view
down below.
The question is
discuss the importance of
budgeting for resources and the successful
execution of AI projects. On the right here
is the response. And
if you scroll down
further, you can
see a more
detailed view for context relevance. There
were six pieces of retrieve
context. Each of them is scored to
be particularly low in their evaluation
scores. It's between 0 and
0.2. And if you pick
any of them and click on
it you can see that
the response is not
particularly relevant to the question that
was asked. You can also scroll back up and explore
some of the other records you can pick
ones, for example, where
the scores are good,
like this one here,
and explore how the application is doing
on various questions, and
where its strengths are,
where its failure modes are,
to build
some intuition around what's working
and what's not. Let's now compare the
previous app to the auto-merging setup
that
Jerry introduced earlier. We will
have three layers now in
the hierarchy, starting with 128 tokens
at the leaf node level 512, one
layer up, and 2048
at the highest layer, so
at each layer
each parent has
four children. Now let's
set up the query engine
for this app setup, the
True Recorder, all identical steps
as the one
for the previous app. And finally,
we are in a
position to run the evaluations.
Now that we have app 1 set
up, we can take a
quick look. And
the total cost is also
about half. And that's because,
recall, this has three layers in
the hierarchy and the chunk
size is 128 tokens instead of the 512,
which is the smallest leaf node
token size for app 0. So that results
in a cost reduction. Notice
also that context relevance
has increased by about
20%. And part of
the reason that's happening is that
And part of the reason
that's happening is that the merging
is likely happening a lot better with
this new app
setup. We can
also drill down and
look at app one in greater
detail. Like before, we can
look at individual records. Let's
pick the same one
that we looked at
earlier, the tab 0.
It's the question about the
importance of budgeting. And now you can see
context relevance is doing better.
Groundedness is
also considerably higher. And if we
pick a sample example response here,
you'll see that, in fact,
it is talking very specifically about budgeting for
resources. So there is
improvement in this particular instance
and also at an aggregate
level. Let me now
summarize some of the key
takeaways from Lesson 4. We walked
you through an approach to evaluate and iterate
with the auto-retrieval
advanced RAG technique. And in particular,
we showed you
how to iterate with different hierarchical
structures, the
number of levels, the
number of child nodes,
and chunk sizes. And
for these different app
versions, you could evaluate
them with the RAG triad
and track experiments to
pick the best structure for your
use case. One
thing to notice
is that not only are
you getting the metrics associated
with the RAG
triad as part of the evaluation,
but the drill down
into the record level
can help you gain
intuition about hyperparameters that
work best with certain doc types. For
example, depending on the nature of
the document, such
as employment contracts
versus invoices, you might find that
different chunk sizes and hierarchical
structures work best. Finally, one other
thing to note
is that auto-merging
is complementary to sentence window retrieval.
And one way to think about
that is, let's say
you have four
child nodes of
a parent. With auto-merging, you might
find that child
number one and child
number four are very relevant to the query
that was asked.
And these then get
merged under the auto-merging paradigm. In contrast, sentence
windowing may not result in this
kind of merging because they are not
in a contiguous section of
the text. That brings
us to the end
of Lesson 4. We
have observed that with
advanced rag techniques such
as sentence windowing and
auto-merging retrieval augmented with
the power of evaluation,
experiment tracking, and iteration,
you can significantly improve
your rag applications. Improve
your RAG applications. In addition,
while the course has focused on these two techniques
and the associated RAG triad for
evaluation, there are
a number of other evaluations
that you can play
with in order to
ensure that your LLM
applications are honest,
harmless, and helpful. This
slide has a list
of some of the ones that
are available out of
the box in TrueLens.
We encourage you to
go play with TrueLens, explore the
notebooks, and take your learning to
the next level.